Cool. Yeah. So, so thanks so much uh
everyone for coming. Um I think you you
have a pretty cool course here. Um and
thanks of course Percy for for inviting
me to to give a talk. Uh so I think in
this class you're mostly talking about
kind of training and how to train the
language models um and and kind of get
to to this place where we can have these
things that that can kind of talk back
to you. Um in today I'm going to talk a
little bit about once you have one of
those models what it looks like from the
other side. uh what it looks like to
actually serve these models um turn you
know to do do inference turn these
things from say electricity into tokens
into into intelligence and also what are
some of the fun research problems and
and research things that you can do um
when you look at it from from that
standpoint
I'll start with some uh sort of high
level motivation uh I think one thing
that's become abundantly clear to all of
us is that we are really going through
almost a new indust industrial
revolution in terms of these models and
their capabilities. Um these slides I
made during my job talks like two years
ago. So the exact examples are getting
pretty old. Uh but you can do you know
human level text generation code
generation uh cursor cloud code uh GPT
5.5
um not not just four uh you can generate
images and videos or understand images
and videos and process them. Um you can
start to understand new modalities. So,
we're starting to see some of the
applications in the sciences in bio um
in and health, DNA models, all these
sorts of things. One of the things that
has really been driving my research for
a while is uh the question of what has
made these advances possible and how can
we improve on them um in the next
generations. And one abundant driver of
these capabilities is really scale. So
again, this is uh at this point a pretty
old um uh figure, but these models have
really scaled up um in in massive ways.
So in 2018, at the beginning of my PhD
in antiquity, uh these were 100 million
parameter models at their largest and
we're like, "Oh my god, these things are
are pretty crazy." By 2019, we thought
that they were too dangerous to release.
That's GPD2. I think in this class you
can train a GPT2 quality model. I'm not
sure if you did. if you tried hard
enough, you could. Um, and uh, yeah, and
today, of course, the you have open
source models that are a trillion
parameters and more. Uh, the frontier is
probably at 5 to 10 trillion parameters.
Um, it's it's pretty exciting. With
these, you have a bunch of new
capabilities like chat, uh, writing
code, analyzing complex text, um, doing
your homework for you, etc.
Um what's really remarkable about this
is that this transition is happening
faster than we think. So certainly
faster than I thought um uh at the
beginning of my PhD a few years ago. So
I I think one really apt analogy and and
the dates actually kind of um match up
in an interesting way. So in 1902 there
are 130,000 working horses in Manhattan.
So these are horses that you don't just
have around for for giggles, but you
actually have them because they they do
they they play some key role. Um and
they would these horses would produce uh
each would produce pounds of manure a
day times 130,000 horses, you have a
real manure problem. So in fact um there
were entire conferences that were just
gathered around the question of entire
academic conferences around what do we
do about all the poop that these horses
produce? So in 1898 they actually had
one of these in New York. Um, and their
conclusion from that conference was
there's nothing we can do about the
horse manure. You just have to hold your
nose um and and deal with it. 10 years
later, by 1912, cars had already
outnumbered horses in Manhattan. So that
10-year transition, you saw this, you
know, the these the these things that
have been around for for centuries um
start to be replaced by by cars.
Um and I think for us for language
models for a lot of the stuff that we do
um that 1912 moment was probably last
year. So at least for me last year I
started writing the majority of my code
using these language models. Most people
in my team do it. Um I tell all my
students to do it. Um except when
they're doing their homework. Um but
this is this is really a really exciting
transition that that we're we're living
through.
One of the things that is really driving
this is a lot of the scale is driven by
um GPU. So uh in a very real sense you
could say GPUs are the new oil. This is
again a a a older announcement but
you're seeing hundreds of billions of
dollars and more of investment into
GPUs.
Um, you know, history rhymes in in
interesting ways uh with the with with
similar things, but their their entire
countries, entire sovereign wealth funds
that are making these things a major
part of of their um of their of their
piece.
And one thing that is really abundantly
clear is that inference is really the
piece. So you can think of inference as
the engine that turns electricity into
intelligence. So the same way that you
know oil is only useful in a uh in a car
if you can have actually an engine that
turns that that oil into useful kinetic
motion. Um inference engines, GPU
kernels, these are the things that that
really turn uh that really turn these
GPUs from from sand like Percy said into
something that we can use today. Um and
I think that's that's clear. So if you
think about it, so these machine
learning models uh they're really just
DAGs of operations. there are some
mathematical object that exists in the
ether. The inference engines, the GPU
kernels, all these pieces. Um, these are
the things that you actually have to
program and and map them down to ML
operations. I think you do some of that
in this class. Uh, I think you implement
some flash attention, so some training
side. Um, but there's a whole world of
complexity when it comes to inference
um, and the inference side of things.
So if you take away nothing from today's
talk, uh I I hope there there's one
thing which is if you understand
inference and understand the inference
engines, if you understand the GPU
kernels that underly a lot of the a lot
of the core technology, you can enable
full stack innovation in machine
learning algorithms. So I'm going to
start with in today's talk a highlevel
overview of kind of the lifetime of a
token. So when you make a request to one
of these models, what happens to that
request? How it goes through the entire
inference service? What are some of the
interesting choices you have to make? Um
and then I'll dive deeper into two uh
kind of more research projects around if
you take certain pieces of this um of
this system. What are questions that you
can ask and and what are some some
things that you can do?
Uh before I get into all the the
technical details, I'll quickly make a
plug. So I'm here representing two
organizations. And so one is UCSD where
I where I have a small lab um and and uh
some some of their work is represented
in this talk. Then I'm also representing
together um who did a bunch of other uh
of the work that's represented in this
talk. Um together is an AI cloud. So
there's GPUs inference fine-tuning um
and all the rest.
Heavy research background so including
Percy. I don't think you can see my
mouse but see he's on the screen. And
then we've got a a big research presence
um behind that. and behind a lot of the
things that that you're going to see in
this talk.
All right, I'll start by kind of giving
a highle overview of a lifetime of a
token. So, when you make a request to a
inference system, what are the different
pieces that are that are going to go
through um and these slides are a crib
from a presentation that my student
Austin made um when uh and and from his
experiences at together. I'll make a
note that all of the slides are
completely AI generated from Nano Banana
Pro. Um, but they're they're pretty good
as long as you don't look too closely at
at the text. So, I'd say at a high level
everything is correct. If you look very
closely, you'll see things that are very
wrong.
Okay. Um, this is a overview of kind of
all the pieces of an inference engine.
So, I'll give a a a highle description
of kind of how it works. So you get a
request in the first thing that's going
to happen is that the request gets
scheduled to various different GPUs. You
might have disagregated prefill and
decode on on different different
machines. Um you'll run that request
against a KP cache to see have I seen
this request or or versions of this
request before? Is there some uh is
there some compute that I can that I can
actually save? Um then you'll start
executing the the kind of the core
machine learning code. Uh so here are
new tokens, here are new operations that
we need to compute. Um there are various
optimizations that you can make. So you
can split that computation across
different machines. You can parallelize
across different nodes. You can
parallelize it within a node across
different GPUs depending on the size of
your model depending on how you can
split up split that up. Um, and I think
one of the exciting things is that as we
are uh as the as the hardware is
developing, we're actually going to
start to see more different choices that
you can make there. Um, but once you
make all those choices, once you execute
all the code at the end, you get the
tokens out, you can say, "Hey chat, what
did Percy mean when he said uh linear
regression?" Um, because I skipped that
day in my class. Um, and you get you get
this whole end to- end experience.
One of the things that I think is useful
to to start thinking about um is what do
these different workloads look like? Um
and there there's quite a different
quite a bit of different things. So if
you this is one of the sites where if
you look too closely like I think some
of the fives turned into S's um but one
of the things that that you want to
think about is when you're actually
serving production traffic it doesn't
necessarily look like certainly doesn't
look like what the the type of tokens
that you see during training. Um but it
also kind of doesn't look like if you
just uh made up um a traffic workload in
your head. So what what is the type of
thing that that that we typically see?
So for a particular workload um you'll
see a particular distribution of input
and output tokens. So uh let's take a
coding workload. So let's say you're
somebody like cursor um where you have
uh your whole codebase is available to
the agent. You're asking questions about
it. Um, typically what that'll look like
is that you'll have a long amount of
input, so tens of thousands of input
tokens. Um, and then depending on how
you've trained your model, the model
might output some amount of thinking
tokens or it might uh output some some
short uh some some short input. And this
will change based on workload. It'll
change based on a model. Um so a
particular a coding workload for example
will look very different from a uh
summarization workload or or a narrative
summarization. So if your work involves
like pasting entire books into a chat
window and then talking back and forth
to figure out what's happening that's
going to look very different than a
standard chat um thing. So if you just
go up to chat and say hey explain to me
first order calculus or whatever um
that's going to have very different
workload shapes.
uh the way that we use language models
today, there's very uh turnbased agentic
workflows. So when you're coding, you go
back and forth with your coding agent,
say, "Hey, do this. No, I didn't mean
that. Do that." Your coding agents
themselves can iterate on the language
models quite a bit. So they might um uh
they might invoke some tools and say,
"GP, search for something in my in my in
my data in my codebase and then take
that and go uh feed it back to the
model. I might try to do an internet
search and look up this thing that my
user asked me. Um so typically you have
these multiple turns um in your
conversation.
The another interesting piece is
different applications will have
different times. So in your if you're in
a fast interactive chatbased loop or if
you're talking on your phone to chat GPT
in the voice mode um you might have
relatively quick responses. If on the
other hand, you've put together a an
aentic workflow where you say, "Hey, go
do this for me. I'm going to leave you
alone and just iterate um on your own,
you'll have a different cadence." If at
some point your agent gets stuck and
it's, "Hey, hey, help. I I need to I
need to ask for advice and you and you
don't notice it, there might be another
gap between turns." So, all of these
things start to define what your
workload looks like. So, how many to how
many new tokens do you get in it every
time? How many tokens are you going to
generate? How many how long is my
session? So, am I a very sticky user who
keeps going back and forth with my
claude agent or am I a or am I a am I a
user who's just going to ask one
question and then leave and come back
the next day? Um, and and of course, how
how long between turns do you have? Um,
I, for example, uh have a chat that I've
had with a chat GPT agent about how I
should set up my workout and my um my
workouts week to week. Um, and I
interact with that chat about once every
other week. Um and uh so that is a very
different traffic pattern than than some
of the other ones. Um and then of course
depending on your application you might
have different targets. So if you have a
if you have a interactive application
you might say I want to get the first
tokens back in less than a second so
that the the agent can say hey I'm
thinking and I'm going to say blah blah
blah blah. Um or I might say uh I know
I'm going to be generating 500 tokens
and I want that whole response to come
back within a certain amount of time so
that my user can read it fast enough. um
and uh and and all these pieces.
So as that as that when that uh request
comes in um there are a few basic pieces
that that come in. I'll I'll rest a bit
on the prefill and decode piece in a
little bit. But so let's say you have
some amount of um text that comes in.
The first thing you're going to is
you're going to tokenize it. Um I think
you're all familiar with that. Um, but
then once there you start getting into a
somewhat complex scheduling regime
because you have to ask questions like,
have I seen these tokens before? Can I
just look up some some of the
activations in a cache? Um, and then you
get to these basically these two uh
major pieces of the actual uh of the
actual machine learning computation. Um,
these are called prefill and decode and
they're very different be. So prefill
means let's say you have 10,000 tokens
that you've never seen before and you
want to go compute um you know what the
activations and what the logic should
be. So 10,000 tokens in one token out.
That's a very computebound operation. So
that actually looks pretty close to the
things that you guys have been looking
at for training time. So when you're
training you have some large amount of
tokens, you write your flash tension
kernel, you run your training loop. Um
prefill is very similar. You just don't
run your backwards pass. And then you
have this thing called decode. So decode
is um when you're then just generating
one token at a time. So you pass in
these 10,000 tokens. It's like, hey,
here's my codebase. Tell me what
function ABC does. Um the model is going
to process the whole prompt and then
start generating one token at a time,
maybe three or four tokens if you have
speculative decoding working. And if you
think about that operation, so every
time you generate a new token, you then
have to run that back through the model.
If you do the math on that, there's
actually not too many flops that you
need to compute. Um so it's going to be
a relatively light um um computation uh
but it's going to be very memory
bandwidth bound. So what that means is
you're going to be running uh you have
to load up the model every time just to
generate a single token. Um at the end
you get uh at the end of that model pass
of course you then have a a a single
number that represents a token that then
gets turned into a string. You probably
do a little bit of processing on that.
So you look for stop tokens. you check
um you know you you might run a safety
check to say oh is is my user trying to
uh hack into the system in a bad way um
etc and then at the out you get the the
nice tokens
um and the inference engine is really
running in this loop kind of waiting for
these requests to come in um so it's
rating so it's running this scheduling
execution uh token sampling loop and and
repeating
So I'll get into a little bit of so now
we can take one step deeper and start to
look at um what does it look like when
you have a system that is processing
many different requests at a time. So we
have this phenomenon called uh this
technique called continuous batching. So
the way to read this uh figure is that
um it is time is flowing downward. So as
you go down there are new requests that
are coming in. Um, so let's say if we go
to step one, you have some long request.
You have a user uh that is asking for um
some uh to to analyze some some long
piece of some long document and the and
the and the engine is going and
generating a bunch of tokens out. You
might have another request comes in um
that that starts to take up um some
resources. So these resources are first
compute resources. You have to run uh
run things over uh multiple requests at
once. They can be memory resources if
you're filling up a KV cache. Um, and
uh, so you'll see these multiple
requests happening at the same time. Um,
after a step that short request might
finish and you get a new request that
comes in. Um, and maybe it's it's
running for a couple steps. Uh, if you
have another request that comes in, um,
maybe it's another very long request. So
that's going to be that orange one in
step four, but maybe you don't have
enough GPU memory. So you need to store
all your KV cache on your GPU. Maybe
you've run out. You might start queuing
for for some reason there. Um then once
that long request is done, you can start
the new request. Um and then etc. You
can watch it run. So already you're
seeing some of the complexity when you
have many different requests uh living
in a system. Um and and how it how it
goes on.
One of the pieces that that's quite
important is this thing called a KV
cache. Um so the way to think about this
is that uh you probably have a lot of
users who are saying hi chat GPT or or
hi claude and then uh theoretically you
don't need to compute new activations
and and run that again for for every
single user. Um or if you have a a long
book that the user has passed in you
compute you run the prefill over that
once and then the next time you get some
addendum to that request the next turn
in the conversation you don't need to
compute um the the whole thing again. So
we we have these mechanisms called KV
caches uh that that use prefix sharing
that say hey I have this new set of
tokens that comes in use a very
traditional data structure like a basic
tree look at which tokens have I seen
before which tokens are new um uh and
then basically do a lookup of what those
activations are going to look like
once you actually have the computation
on the GPUs. There's various ways to
split it. Um, so I I'm not sure if you
if you talked about this too much, but
let's say you have a trillion parameter
model and you're running on uh let's
call it 280 gigabyte GPUs. Um, you're
not going to be able to fit the full the
whole model onto each GPU. Um, so there
are various ways that you might split
it. So you might take every tensor and
split it uh four ways across four GPUs.
This is called tensor parallelism. Or uh
today we have a lot of the
state-of-the-art models are mixture of
experts models. So they have the you
have these individual experts that get
selectively activated depending on
different tokens. You can split those
across different GPUs. The choices that
you make at this at this point will
determine what are the bottlenecks. How
many uh you know how many GPUs do you
need to run your model? Uh how many
sessions can you serve at the same time
um etc.
One of the big thing that that that
happens is that we tend to split preill
and decode onto different GPUs,
different sets of machines. Um, and
that's because they have very different
compute um bottlenecks and compute
characteristics. So prefill looks a lot
like what you guys do during training.
Uh, you you just run it. It's very
flopheavy. Um, you can really use use
the most out of your GPUs. Decoder on
the other hand is very memory bandwidth
heavy um because you're not doing that
much compute but you still have to load
up all the um all the uh all the model
weights at the same time. These things
will also take different amounts of
time. So prefill will typically take a
lot longer than a single decode step,
but you're going to be running a lot
more decode steps because you will run
prefill once for a prompt, you'll run
decode uh once for for every token that
you generate. So a very basic
optimization that um that that pretty
much we've all started adopting is that
you'll run pre-fill on one set of
workers, decode on another set of
workers um so that you can specialize
those two computations to to different
pieces of the stack. Um and there turns
out there there's a lot of innovation
that you can have when you when you have
these splits. uh some things that you
might have heard of that when Nvidia
bought Grock, so Nvidia the king of GPUs
buys this new kind of um infancy chip.
One of the reasons is that uh the decode
workload is so different from the
prefield workload that if you're looking
at decode, you can uh you can be using
very different chips. Um so uh for
example, in the next generation of
hardware, Nvidia is planning on using
its GPUs for the prefill side, using
these LPU Gro chips for the decode. You
see similar things um with Cerebra. So
OpenAI has this compute partnership with
Cerebras. It's another chip that's much
better at decode. Uh there are other
companies like Sabbonova and so on um
that are also making bets along various
parts of this space.
Uh here here's a fun one a interesting
one. So um when you actually start
deploying these inference engines at
scale, so when you're starting to serve
trillions of tokens or more a day, uh
you start to get some pretty nasty bugs.
So this is a set of bugs. I think most
of these happened um in uh I want to say
late last year um with some of the
open-source inference engines. Um and uh
and and basically so you'll one of the
characteristics of these large scale
systems is that something that will work
well at a small scale will inevitably
start breaking at a large scale. So
we're talking um events that happen with
0.001%
of the time or or less. Um some of these
uh can be uh so nan. So sometimes um
you'll have a kernel that is very
slightly wrong but um but the conditions
for triggering it are very rare. um and
you will start having some of your
logits uh turn into nans halfway through
the uh uh halfway through the
computation. When that happens, we we
figured out that the model starts
outputting the same token. So I think
some model the the output just starts
saying hi h highi highi highi high after
a while um or or start outputting
exclamation points um and you get caught
into these loops. Um uh another model at
some point uh someone made a change to
how you're handling tool calls. So tool
calls are uh when the model says hey I
want to I want to make an internet
search or something like that. So the
model will actually say go do an
internet search and then your end
harness has to then go use old-fashioned
code to do the internet search. Um at
some point um uh those tool calls stop
being processed correctly um in in one
of the engines. And the symptom for that
was that the completion length um shot
up because um the the model would say
hey make an internet search and then it
would it would uh usually usually when
the model was behaving correctly it says
hey make an internet search I'm done go
return to the user uh go do that
whatever but in this case uh it wasn't
returning correctly so it would say hey
make an internet search hey make an
internet search hey I don't know why
there's no internet search going on it
would just get into this very long doom
loop um uh for tens of thousands of
tokens
Um there's another one that um uh this
one was was interesting because it
actually took out I think a number of
inference providers at the same time um
and actually got blamed on a
quantization issue. Um but actually what
was happening was a much more subtle bug
where um uh the model would just
suddenly randomly start to output
Chinese characters um when when it had
no reason to. So um uh for some models
at sometime there's some speculation oh
they must have fine-tuned on a Chinese
model because my model certainly starts
I ask it a question in English and
starts speaking back to me in Chinese.
Um actually what was happening is that
uh there was just an off by one error in
one of the kernels and it would be a
very subtle bug. So sometimes um you
would read in some extra uh some extra
uninitialized memory space um in from
your GPU run it through attention then
at the end of that whole process you get
a random Chinese character then the
model will go why did I start suddenly
thinking Chinese I must be uh I must be
you know the user must be asking me a
question in Chinese and then it will
just go veer off into Chinese. Um, so,
uh, sometimes when this happens, it's
because the model has legitimately been
trained to say, uh, to to to think in
Chinese. Sometimes, um, it can just be
off by one bug, um, in somebody's code.
Um, some interesting things that that
are starting to happen uh, in in a lot
of the more advanced inference stacks.
Um so a major piece of running um large
production systems is that you want to
have as large of a KV cache as possible.
So it is best if you can uh cache
requests from many different users or
from the same user across many different
sessions um and and be able to run as
many sessions as possible. Uh you first
start this by storing your KV cache on
GPU um and then you quickly run out of
GPU memory. So the next you can start
storing into CPU DRAM. Um so uh if
you're paying attention to um Jensen's
keynotes, he's he's recently started
getting very obsessed with CPU
performance. Um one of the reasons is
because uh a past generation of CPUs was
actually really slow. Um and as a result
started bottlenecking a bunch of um a
bunch of very important workloads. Um
and and as a result, you start paying
attention because if your $500,000,000
machine is being bottlenecked by the
thousand CPU um that you purchase to
kind of put on top of it, um that that's
not a great place. One of the reasons
that can happen is that you might be
storing your KV cache on CPU memory. Um
and so you really care about the speed
of being able to read that KV cache
back. Uh next, you might put uh more KV
cache onto the disk itself. Um and then
you start caring about SSDs. um and SSD
space. Um again, you've probably heard
these rumblings about OpenAI buying up
all the SSD, all the DRAM in the world.
Part of the reason is for stuff like
this um where you want to store as much
stuff in your KV cache as you can.
And then of course when you're actually
building your engine, there's this
complicated dance of uh you know, I
haven't seen the these tokens in a
while. Maybe I'll evict it, send it onto
the CPU or send it into disk or send
into some other global store. When I get
a new request in, I have to go look, I
have to go wait for those to come in,
fetch them, load them up into my thing,
and then and then we're happy.
>> CPU offloading isn't like a special kind
of workload that gets offloaded like for
for like something fast, you don't want
to do this, right?
>> Time to hit a SSD is very long.
>> Can you repeat the question?
>> Yes. Yeah. Yeah. So the question is um
so for this offloading is it a
particular type of workload that that
you offload? Um so here we actually get
to some pretty I'm sure none of you guys
have taken an operating systems class
but you should take your operating
systems classes. Um you actually get to
some pretty classic scheduling things.
So this uh you could have this diagram
except for like the GPU things on the
right looks exactly like a operating
systems diagram that you might have seen
in the 70s or the 80s. Um because we
used to have this problem where if you
opened up too many applications on your
computer uh you would run out of CPU
memory and then you'd have to put those
applications onto the disk. Um and it is
exactly the same workload. Um so uh
ideally so uh so here actually on the
left side the nano banana hallucinated
evictions for least recently used which
is actually a pretty decent heristic.
Um, there's probably some OS paper
somewhere that says that LRU is within
2x of of what you can do. That's
optimal. Of course, the best thing that
you want to do is if you could predict
the future, you would say you would
know, oh, I'm about to have a request
come in of a particular kind. Let me go
prefetch that memory in. Um, it might
actually be possible to predict the
future. So, for example, when you go
into your chat app and you bring up some
old conversation from a month ago,
that's a very strong signal that you're
going to go start asking a question
about it, you might then want to go load
up that um load that up onto a GPU. But
yeah, so in a perfect world, you predict
the future. If you can't predict the
future, use various heristics. Um and
really, it's a question of
uh how much traffic you want to put onto
your GPU footprint. Um, I've never
talked to anybody who wants to put less
traffic onto their GPUs. Um, so yeah, I
think modulo or subject to those SLAs's
that we kind of splashed up at the at
the beginning, um, you want to serve as
much traffic as you can,
right? Um, some fun things that are
starting to happen. So uh in the last
generation of Blackwell GPUs, Nvidia
started putting together uh these new
GPUs called NVL sendme 2 grace Blackwell
chips. So these are 72 GPUs that are
connected with really fast interconnect.
Um and so you start to do things like uh
how can I split my trillion parameter
model across all 72 GPUs? Does this make
any sense? Um what does it buy me? Um uh
what what happens? How do I start to
think about fault tolerance? So, um,
these things can fail a lot for various
different reasons. Uh, one reason is
that the, uh, the connectors are kind of
flimsy, like they're made of plastic,
not made of metal. So, if you like jam
the thing in too much, then, uh, then
your cables are going to like bend the
things a little bit and then you get
really flaky envy links. Um, so, uh,
which is a whole thing in itself, but
what happens when, okay, so this is the
AI generation. So, it's put a fan into
the into the chips, which which doesn't
quite make sense. Um, one of the things
that you want to start thinking about is
if I've taken a model, split it across
64 GPUs, I'm serving production traffic
against millions of users, trillions of
tokens, what do I do when a single GPU
goes down? Um, is there some way to make
that fall tolerant? And and there
there's a lot of fun things to think
about there.
Um, and then of course, uh, you're
starting to see these models have a
million contexts or more. Um, how do you
actually process it? Do you split that
context across many different GPUs? um
uh h how do you do these different
things?
Um so I want to dive uh ju just very
briefly highlight one set of one example
of an optimization that you can start to
make when you start looking at this
whole uh at this whole process from a
systems level. So this is a a piece of
work that we put out together um a few
months ago called cache aware prefill
decode disagregation. Um and it's a very
simple optimization. and it's like two
lines of code uh in the routing layer uh
but can actually make a pretty big
difference. So the basic idea is uh you
have all these requests that are coming
in. Most of them are going to be turn
based uh turnbyturn uh requests in a
conversation where somebody's already
started a conversation. Um but let's say
your average conversation lasts 10 turns
um and then the the user goes away. That
suggests that okay 10% of your requests
are going to be very fresh very new
requests. So, when you have a new
request that comes in that's going to be
thousands of tokens, it's going to look
very different. Um, it's going to be a
lot more expensive to compute. You don't
necessarily want to put that prefill
against a short conversation that um
where where you're halfway through a
conversation. So, someone past in a book
and says, "Hey, talk to me about this
book." You don't want that running at
the same time as someone who's midway
through a conversation. Like, chat,
explain to me um uh the why 1 plus 1
equals 2. um in chat is like 1 plus 1
equals two because numbers and whatnot
and you're like oh I don't get it. You
don't want that like very short uh
question and answering to happen in the
same time on the same GPUs as the very
long um uh as the very long request. So
you can put together this this really
simple uh router that says okay if we
have a new request that comes in that's
a very low cache hit rate send it to one
set of GPUs so that those can all um
process things uh together and then send
all my other warm requests to another
set of prefill nodes. Turns out if you
do this you can get up to 40% faster
serving with these very simple um very
very simple optimizations. So like that
that's one set of things. I'd say the
the way that I would characterize where
we are in terms of uh the the research
and these techniques is that we're very
early. So um this is the type of thing
that uh in 10 20 years they're going to
look back on and be like oh why are
these guys talking about this? Does
isn't this already obvious to folks? Um
uh but really it's because we're
starting to see these things running
them um at production in new ways seeing
the these new bits of traffic um in uh
in in new ways.
All right. So so that was kind of a
overview of the inference uh you know
life of a kernel. Um now I'm gonna talk
about two interesting research projects
that are very much uh inspired by some
of the things that we see when serving
things at Ender. So this first one we're
gonna be talking about uh language model
language model decode and how you can
make it go a lot faster with these
things called mega kernels. Uh this is a
collaboration between Stanford and
together.
So the fundamental challenge when you're
running decode. So decode is the process
by okay you've process your prompt and
now you're generating one token at a
time. The fundamental challenge is that
um you have to run the whole model to
generate a single token. Um so that
means that instead of using all this big
parallelism that you get with a GPU that
you can do during prefill or training um
you've now turned this massively
parallel system um into basically a
glorified memory loader.
And one of the things that that makes
this um extra challenging is that the
way that we typically write down kernels
and and run a model is that uh we will
write down kernels and and program
things one operation at a time. So you
guys can probably understand why this
is. So kernels tend to be pretty
challenging to write. I'm sure you guys
all had a lot of fun writing flash
attention. Um but that means that
typically what we do is we look at all
the different operations in a um in a
language model and we will run uh a we
will write a single kernel for that
operation at a time. So this makes
things a lot easier uh to program
because you just have to run your write
your norm kernel or your map kernel or
attention kernel
but um you end up seeing uh it ends up
introducing a lot of downtime into your
system. Um, so this is a example of what
it might look like when you're running
inference across your kernel. So this is
uh this is obviously a cartoon but the
example is drawn from a a a particular
attention inference kernel. Um, the way
to read this is that on the x-axis you
have time. So time is flowing from left
to right. On the y-axis you have all the
different little semi uh all the
different little uh streaming
multipprocessors on your GPU. So on a
H100 there's 132 of these. On the B200
there's I think 148 etc. The bars
indicate useful work. So when there's a
bar here you have different um you have
a one of the processors on the GPU is
actually doing work and the empty space
is just waiting. So you're just waiting
for other operations to finish um so
that you can have something else go on.
And so basically uh you get into you get
into this position where no matter how
uh how well you try to write the kernel
you're you're always going to have
downtime in your GPU. So you're going to
have things like kernel launch. So the
kernel launch and kernel tearown that's
these big uh gaps in in the red and the
yellow. Uh you're going to have these
things called tail effects. So this is
just um the same way uh that if you have
a short prompt that that gets processed
with a very long prompt. This same thing
goes all the way down to the basic
attention operation. If you're
processing a batch of inputs and one
input is very short, one input is very
long, you're going to be waiting for the
very long input to finish.
Um, and then because uh you're tearing
you're running these across multiple
kernels, uh, you will actually start to
see these gaps between kernels start to
add up.
So, one thing that that we put together
to try to solve this is this thing
called a mega kernel. So this is
basically saying um instead of treating
each operation in the model as its own
operation writing kernel for it instead
let's write a single kernel to cover
multiple operations at once. Uh this is
similar to the fusion that you see in
flash attention um except done more
aggressively um across a larger number
of things. And in particular what it
does is it turns a GPU from a single uh
device a single operation is you start
thinking of the GPU as a massive
distributed system and saying okay I
have all this work that I need to get
done. Some of it has dependencies on on
other stuff. So that red stuff uh has
some dependencies on some of the green
bars. Um how can I schedule it? How can
I distribute the work uh to maximize my
GPU utilization?
Uh if you do this just to the attention
inference corner you get 30 to 70% speed
ups. Um and then the nice thing is that
you can actually do this to the whole
model. Um so this is one layer of a
llama 1B uh model. So here we've
basically taken the entire uh the entire
layer and put it together into one
kernel. If you look at all these
different bars, you see things are
overlapped in in really weird ways. Uh
that's because we we are now starting to
overlap let's say a weight load from the
next from the layer uh into the into the
attention um or starting to run parts of
reduction before before the attention
operation is over.
Um here here's one here's one
interesting example. So uh here's one
thing that you can do. So uh if you look
at modern LMS you have the in the
attention layer you have the QKV
projections. you're gonna add some rope
scaling to it. Um, so that's these blue
blue lines. So those blue lines are QKV
plus rope. Um, and then the orange
lines, this is the beginning of the of
the attention. So one of the insights is
that uh you can start um loading in your
KV cache into your attention before
you're finished with QKV. Um, and
particularly during decode, some of
these orange bars with some of these
circles, you start the KV cache load
while the QKV plus rope is still
running. And then once QKV is done, then
you have your new query tokens, you can
run the rest of the attention operation.
So basically when you when you have
these fine grained when you have this
fine grain control of GPUs, you can
start some operations before others are
over.
Here's another one. Um so here, so
again, the orange is the the is the
first part of the attention computation.
The red is the O projection that comes
after attention. Um and you have your O
projection start loading the weights
before your attention operation is over.
Um we we put this together uh in a very
in a relatively complex CUDA framework
um with basically instruction an
instruction based abstraction where we
can implement each subkernel um in in
its own file and then have a big
virtualized shared memor memory system
to uh to to orchestrate the the running
of these operations.
Um, and to to do this, we put together
this library called Thunderkittens. Um,
which is a uh a a one of these kernel
writing libraries. You can think of it
as almost like Triton except more
low-level, a lot more fine grain control
um over things.
The payoff is you get near speed of life
light decoding inference. Uh, so the
these numbers are actually a lot better
now. Um, but the the mega kernel is
shown by this bar in teal. Um, and you
can see it runs a lot faster than some
of the other state-of-the-art engines.
Uh, and on the H100, it's achieving 72%
bandwidth utilization. Um, which is near
the speed of light on the GPU. So, if
you say, uh, if you just ignore all the
complexities of what we're doing here
and say how fast can the GPU physically
go to do this operation, we are pretty
close 72% of of that speed of light.
So one interesting bit there is a
takeaway from that section is that if
you have very deep control of the
kernels and the an understanding of the
hardware can start to enable very
different compute paradigms. Um and all
these things you only see when you start
playing with with inference at a deep
level.
Okay. Now I'll talk about um something
that that's a little bit new. So this is
uh now getting into the realm of new
architectures. Um and we're gonna be I'm
gonna be talking about this this new
model called PERS. So this is uh some
work that comes out of my UCSD lab um
led by Hayden and then also in
collaboration with these two folks um
Zachary and Taylor.
Okay. So I'm going to come back to this.
So uh at the beginning of the talk I
talked about hey all these new
capabilities are coming because you're
starting to scale these models and
parameters and data. With parse we
wanted to ask another question which is
is this the only way you have to scale
or is it potentially is there
potentially something else some other
way that you can get this this quality
and with parse we wanted to this was
basically our take on a technique called
loop transformers where you take some
blocks of your transformer and you run
them in a loop. So instead of having
your your tokens go um all like one
layer at a time through the model at
some point you say hey uh as you're
going through just send it back through
through that loop at at a time. Um there
you're going to see there there's a
couple different pieces here. So one is
uh we use some state space model theory
some SSM theory uh to kind of stabilize
this operation. Naively if you just run
this and and let the thing train uh we
saw that the thing was going to blow up.
Um and then the other thing is we
started to see some interesting scaling
laws that suggest that you want to be
scaling the recurrence um of these
recurrent models as you increase the
data. Um so uh you uh in order to make
the best use out of your parameters, you
want to actually be reusing them
somewhat.
Um first I'll talk about a little bit of
motivation of why we found this looping
problem to be very interesting. Um so
the basic idea is uh let's say you have
some activation uh that's going through
part of your model. At some point it
hits the these looped blocks and it's
just going to run the same activation is
going to run through that same layer
some number of times. So that that
purple block is the recurrent block. Um
and then at the end you you get the
thing that comes back.
So uh there are some advantages of this.
So you can keep your parameters constant
but it gives you a dial to increase your
flops. Um so what when if you think that
flops more flops equals higher quality
this is a way to increase your quality
without paying a higher parameter cost.
Um another thing is there's this old
work old is a relative term from a few
years ago that suggests that you
actually get higher explicricity there
expressivity there are things that you
uh that you can't um that you can't
express with the same number number of
parameters that you can't express with
these looped models.
Um, and one of our driving questions was
what's the best quality per parameter?
What's the best intelligence per
parameter or intelligence per parameter
in data that that these things will will
allow you to do?
Um, there were some promising initial
results. So, this is a paper from Tom
Goldstein's group at um in Maryland um
that suggested, hey, this thing might be
better than transformers. Um, you know,
the these are some some some results on
on the arc tasks. Um, and there's also a
bunch of Twitter hype because about a
week before we released Parse, uh, some
dude from OpenAI said that Claude Mythos
is a recurrent is a looped language
model. Um, I don't think it's right. Uh,
I think he was just making it up, but as
a result, um, uh, it it really blew up
um, in Twitter on on in speculation
right before this. Um,
eventually he had to write this blog
post being like, "Hey, my bad. I just
made that up. It's none of it's true."
Um, but it was sufficiently interesting
to go. So, we were working on it before
before this Twitter hype. Um, but but I
think they're they're there's something
interesting something uh interesting to
look at here.
Now, one problem with these looped
models is is if you looked at any of
them and you tried to train them and
then you changed anything about the
training algorithm but at all. So, if
you change the learning rate um by by a
little bit, you'd suddenly start to see
these models blow up. So if you did a
simple thing like a learning rate sweep,
you'd see nine times out of 10 this
model just isn't isn't going to
converge. It's going to blow up. You're
going to get nans. You're going to get
these big loss spikes. Um and so we were
saying, hey, there seems to be something
wrong with this. So if you're ever
training a model and you're actually
scaling it up and you see there are
these big loss spikes that suggest
something has gone very wrong with your
training process, you should take a
deeper look and and try to figure out
what what happened. In previous work,
there were some hacks like you can put
norms in every layer to figure out
what's happening or you know just pick
two e the the learning rate of 2 e minus
4. Don't pick any of the the other
learning rates. But we were thinking hey
uh the existence of these lo spikes
suggests that there's probably something
um more uh deeper going on.
Um and so we took a bit of a
mathematical state space modelesque
approach uh to the stabilization
question.
Um our basic insight was uh you can look
at this process. Um so actually if you
if you look at this process you try to
think about try to how to analyze it an
analytically it's going to be very
complicated because this big RB block
has tons of parameters there's all sorts
of nonlinearities there's a softmax
there's uh and rope and and all these
other things. So um if you try to
analyze it analytically it's quite
complex. Our insight was we were just
saying okay let's actually just look at
the residual of this thing. Um so how is
this activation changing from block to
block? Um our first empirical
observation was hey it actually doesn't
change that much. So each of these
residual blocks is not is maybe changing
the vector a little bit but not really
uh uh having a a massive impact.
And as a result uh how can we so maybe
we can actually model this. maybe we can
actually um look look at what's
happening more deeply.
And so what we did is we went and wrote
down a dynamic system over this
residual. And when we did, we realized
there's a couple pieces in here that uh
when you look at the when you look at
how you write down the model might look
relatively
um uh relatively benign but actually end
up being being a huge bit. So what we
did was we said okay there's all this
nonlinear stuff there's this attention
there's this uh gal there's this big
feed forward network with the with the
act with the uh uh intermediates and
stuff um we're going to all put that
into a box we're just going to call that
r um and this r is going to be some big
nonlinear thing um but we're going to uh
we're going to we're going to put it
just just stick it to the side what
you're left with is um these a and b
matrices. So this B matrix is some uh uh
some transformation over your your
initial uh your initial vector. So what
is that first vector before you start
the loop? And then this a vector is this
a matrix is how do you transform that
residual um in in each loop. And what we
did is we said hey this this simple
thing if you take all the complexity of
the transformer and stick it to stick it
to the side you have a relatively simple
way of looking at all the previous loop
transformers. Um and in in previous
cases you do end up making some pretty
normal decisions. So in in one case you
just say oh uh the you you you just
treat it as the as the identity you're
just going to add things. In another
case it's a fully learnable matrix.
Um and then we said okay what happens if
we just so the the resid we we observed
empirically that these [music] a and b
matrices are actually dominating uh the
the magnitude of this equation. What
happens if you just drop that
complicated nonlinear piece? What do you
get out? Well, you get out actually a
pretty simple system that if you use
high school calculus, you can just solve
it to figure out what the answers are
going to be. So, here's the closed form
solution. Uh you can actually compute
what is given what the initial
activation is and what that um initial
injection is. You can actually just uh
empirically compute what what the
activation is going to look like at time
at step t plus one.
And you notice a couple things. So this
thing is dominated by uh these these a
matrices and empir and and especially
this a matrix that you are powering up
to a large degree.
Um and from here what we realize is that
there's this quantity called the
spectral radius of this a. So spectral
radius is basically like another word
for norm. Um one way that you can look
at this is that uh uh you're taking this
matrix you're powering it up to to huge
amounts. Um if this matrix can learn to
be something like let's say that this
matrix uh you know if you go to scalers
imagine that this matrix is two and then
this t is like 16 or something. You've
now taken this activation you've blown
it up to 2 to the^ of 16 and it's and
it's really big. Uh and this starts to
explain some of those big loss spikes.
Um and in particular what we found is
that the choices that you make for these
A and B matrices uh in that that people
have made in these previous papers are
either we call them marginally stable or
unstable um uh unstable make the system
unstable.
And so with parse a we said okay well we
figured out this thing where or if you
if you take this particular look at it
um and you let these A and B do whatever
they want you're going to get things
that really explode. What if we just
constrain A and B such that uh if you
run the math they're not not going to
explode. So for A uh what we did is we
said okay uh we're effectively going to
make that A matrix a negative diagonal
matrix. So if you um power that up you
the term eventually goes to zero so it
doesn't blow up. um this speed matrix
we're going to put a stick a really
simple linear norm against it um because
the speed matrix actually only gets
applied once and doesn't really blow up.
If you compute the spectral radius is
now going to be less than one. It's now
actually going to be a stable system.
Now if you go train this model what we
saw uh is that you actually saw stable
loss curve. So parse is this uh
stabilized thing where we
reparameterized a and b. You can see
that even with this the 6E minus 4
learning rate that was so bad for for
the other models, you actually got got a
stable model at the end. Um and you see
that with with doing this you can
naturally constrain the the state norm
of the of the activations. Um uh so two
pieces here. So that orange baseline is
just a completely unconstrained model.
You can see it blows up goes to 10 to
the 19th. This blue line is actually a
um a model where uh where you are
applying a norm to it. Um so what
happens here is that the model is
actually trying to expand the
activations cuz um because it's saying
oh with more room I can uh I can
represent different things better. I can
you know put these different concepts
further away from each other or whatnot.
Um and then you're applying norm to it
to take that big thing that's trying to
expand. Then you try to norm it back
down to one. Um, and then you have this
big uh the these two pressures that are
kind of fighting against each other that
manifest in loss spikes. So even though
on the right your norms are very good,
you're not seeing the activation
actually blow up. Um, you do see that
the loss uh can can do some pretty
gnarly things.
Um, so basically this this pretty simple
change in the activations uh can
stabilize the training, stabilize these
recurrent loops.
Uh so it's not only a more stable
system, you actually also get more high
higher quality models. Um so this is a
uh this is a table where we are
comparing parse models against uh a
previous loop transformer called
recurrent depth models. So you can see
higher performance across a a variety of
applications. Um so you see parse
outperforms the previous loop models and
also outperforms strong transformer
baseline. So this transformer is like
one of the nano chat ones where a bunch
of people are trying to uh just get it
to learn as fast as it can. Um and these
parade models if you take that same
basic transformer architecture start
looping it um and then stabilize it you
get uh better perplexities better um
better end toend quality as well.
And then one and then we started to run
some very basic scaling laws here. Um
and here our question was okay this is
really really cute. uh you can do this
looping thing to to make things better,
but really should you like is there any
evidence that that there's something
here that that we want to be doing um uh
looping more aggressively?
Um so here I'll take a step back. Uh a
few years ago there there's all this
work on uh you know as we started to
enter this this regime where you wanted
to scale up all these models a natural
question is should I make the models
bigger or should I just train on more
data? Um so a few years ago folks
started to ask you know how should I
scale these two quantities with each
other? Should I scale model parameters?
Should I scale data? Um and we came up
with all these very complicated um power
law curves uh that all look like this.
They're very pretty. There's lots of
colors. What you want to look out for is
basically um uh sorry. What you want to
look out for is if that curve is going
down and to the right, it suggests you
should be scaling both data and
parameters at the same time. Um, if we
were going straight down, that would
mean uh, you know, just increase your
training data. There's there's no
there's no need to increase your
parameters. If it's going, if it's flat,
just going straight to the right, that
means uh, you know, don't increase your
data at all. Just increase your
parameters. Um, but you see it's going
down and to the right that means you
should scale data and parameters at the
same time. And now you see this, you
know, you train a one trillion parameter
model on 35 trillion tokens. Um, and you
get better quality.
So our question was okay where does
recurrence fit into this and there are a
couple right so down into the right
means you want to scale data and prams
there are a couple possibilities so uh
with recurrence
um and uh so for example you might
conclude you should never run recurrence
like it's better to just keep the same
single recurrent model you might
conclude uh you should do a ton of
recurrence or maybe only some recurrence
to the to to the bit um what we're
showing here is at least in these
initial scaling laws. Uh so all of these
curves are isometric and isopram
isoflop. So each of these curves is a
model. So on the left and the right you
have the same number of parameters. Um
as you go down as you change the colors
we are increasing the amount of flops I
use to train to train to train the model
by increasing the amount of data. So
here we are varying data and varying the
number of recurrences.
What we find is that in both of these
models you see this down into the right
trend again. So what this is suggesting
is that for these fixed parameter um
training things uh as you increase the
amount of data you should actually also
be increasing the amount of recurrences
um that that that you have.
Uh we find that these recurrences follow
some you know pretty classic power laws.
Um so you can actually start to predict
uh you can get these scaling laws to
start to predict quality as you scale
recurrences and your tokens jointly.
>> Question for
recurrence. Yeah. What about the jointly
from the scaling?
>> Yeah. So, we had this like really
complex 3D figure that showed like like
recurrences and data and parameters and
it kind of like pointed also like
whatever down and to the right and like
down that way at the same time. Um, so
like if you believe that figure, it
suggests you should be scaling all three
uh together. Yeah, but that figure was
just really hard to look at because it
was kind of like 3D and weird. Um but
yeah so yeah the these power laws
suggest when you're increasing data you
should be increasing recurrence. Um and
then you have other power laws that
suggest when you're increasing data you
should be increasing parameters. So um
obviously you should increase well it
suggests that you should increase all
three of them if you can. Um, but one
piece here is that if you're going to
fix your model size and you're going to
increase the amount of data, you should
also be increasing the the recurrence,
which is interesting because as far as I
know, all of our models today have no
recurrence in them. So, they're all kind
of like at the very left of of these
curves. Um, and they all have a ton of
data, which suggests that there might be
something slightly better that we could
be doing uh when training these models,
right? And here here's just that
experiment um in in another way. So on
the orange curve you have so here we
fixed the uh the model size. The orange
curve is a fixed depth model. So this is
like a traditional transformer model.
The blue curve is um uh when you fix the
flop budget uh where do you hit on the
curve uh for a for a looping model. Uh
so here uh these the orange and blue
dots have been trained with the same
number of flops but a different amount
of data. Um but they're the same size.
When you get to that number of flops by
increasing recurrences as well as and
not just increasing data, you start to
get smaller validation losses. Um which
again suggests it might be the case that
we should be looping all of our big uh
all of our big pre-training runs.
Yep. So, so that's parse. Um, if I want,
if I take a little step back, um, and
kind of go go back to to the big
takeaway of the talk, um, I think
hopefully I've given you a little sense
today of if you understand the inference
of these models, if you understand the
GPU kernels, uh, you understand all the
pieces um, that goes into it, you can
really start to enable full stack
innovation in machine learning
algorithms. So whether that's through a
new routing algorithm that lets you
serve more more traffic or serve traffic
in a different way or new kernels that
allow you to run part of your system way
faster or new architectures that say um
you know if you have a lot fewer
parameters you can fit them in a subset
of your GPUs in a different way reduce
the amount of communication. Um these
are all different pieces of that of that
question of the of that really research
problem that that we're seeing today.
Um, and yeah, hopefully uh I've inspired
at least one of you in this room to to
go take a deeper look at some of that.
Yeah. So, with that, thanks. Happy to
take a few questions. [applause]
>> Okay, we have about five 10 minutes for
questions. So, if you have a question,
raise your hand.
>> Yeah.
For today, I guess like are you uh
creating from scratch on the loot? I
guess I was wondering if you could kind
of take a matrix.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, yeah. So, yeah, great
question. So, the question was with
parse, are we training from scratch? Is
there anything you can do with
pre-trained models? Um, so there was a
really troll blog post from someone a
few months ago where he was like, hey, I
won some like uh some leaderboard
competition without training a single
thing. what he did was he actually
looped a like two or three layers in a
quen model um by and just saw that on
some math things it started having
higher quality. Uh so we have a little
bit of look work trying to look into
this that may be coming out soon. Um but
there there could be some models where
if you do a little bit of looping just
to the pre-trained model you can get a
higher quality thing. Um which is really
weird. Like it it kind of disturbs me
like I don't know why why that would
possibly be the case. Um, but yeah,
we'll we'll be yeah, we're we're quite
interested in this. I think we'll be
looking at it and hopefully if I can
convince Hayden, he'll be staring at the
uh at the activations at the actual
weights to figure out why when you loop
it, it it gets better.
>> Maybe just to follow up on that. So, you
talked about computer optimality for the
loop models. Can you speak about the
inference implications and the memory
and how that um can make you go faster?
>> Yeah. So one of the reasons that I was
personally very excited in uh these
loops things is that uh one of the big
bottlenecks to serving inference
efficiently actually ends up being GPU
memory. So if you have fewer parameters
you can fit for example more KV cache um
or you can uh do less communication
because you need to split your model
against fewer GPUs and things like that.
So there's actually a lot of flexibility
that a smaller model will will get you.
Um, I also had this dream that if you
could make the recurrent block small
enough, um, you could actually write a
little mega kernel to to just do that
recurrent in a little very fast mega
kernel loop. Um, so far we haven't been
able to make those blocks small enough,
but I think it's it's it's quite
interesting. Um, certainly with the next
generation of the LPU, the Grock chips
are coming with Nvidia things, those are
like those have like 250 megabytes of
memory or something like that. So you
the thing that you'll be able to fit
into them is very very small. but maybe
you can design something that will
actually fit into them and then uh you
can just keep your weights in memory the
whole time and just run your activations
through as quickly as you can. So there
are kind of nonlinear benefits that you
can get if you can cross some of these
thresholds um that I'm hoping that that
we'll be able to get to pretty soon.
>> Yeah.
talked about
curious I guess the trade-offs are
always like strictly optimal
>> great great uh so the question is what
are the trade-offs for micro kernels um
the trade-offs are people's blood sweat
and tears um so mega kernels turns out
they're very very labor intensive to
write um so uh to give you some some
context I think a full talented kernel
engineer Over the course of a year,
we'll probably be able to write mega
kernels for one hardware for two or
three models for like batch sizes one to
16. You go batch size 17, you're like,
nope, start over. Got got to go again.
Um, so they're very very challenging to
write and together. We're trying to put
together some compilers that can
automate some of that process. Um, but
it's a very I'd say it's a very
challenging thing to do. I think the
basic mega kernel idea has become it's
kind of you know gone in peaks and
troughs over the last few decades when
it comes to GPU programming. Um yeah so
if you can do it it will go super fast
you will never be able to go faster. Um
but it just takes a lot of energy and a
lot of lot of effort.
>> Cool. Um maybe I can ask a question.
Yeah.
>> So can we talk a little bit more about
uh code design? Um and
>> in particular you mentioned all these
new hardware like rock and cerebrus on
the inference side. So if you're
designing a model and you know that's
going to be the serving platform. How
should you be changing your
architecture?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think there's there's a
couple things that you should look at.
So one is uh you are going to be most
constrained by memory first. So if you
know that you're going to be taking a
model and serving it on a uh on a
particular you know cerebra strip you
want to go look at the cerebra wafer
figure out how much memory you have um
and then size your model so that it can
fit there with enough KV cache or or
whatever to to spare. Um if you look at
carefully at the Chinese models that are
coming out uh they've started making
some interesting choices that suggest
they might be starting to think about
the Huawei chips that that are coming
out. um you'll see uh quantization
choices that people make. So if you have
a model that you're intending to serve
on Nvidia GPUs, for example, Nvidia's
Neotron model that they released, uh you
will train that model in NV FP4. This is
a FP4 format that is proprietary to
Nvidia chips. If you're not going to run
it on on Nvidia chips, like if you're
AMD, then you're going to run this other
format called MX FP4. They each have
their pros and cons. Um, but yeah, so
you you'll make these these kind of
subtle choices based on the hardware
that you're choosing.
>> I think there was a question over there
>> for per se. I was wondering if it's ever
if you just care about compute optimal
training, is it ever optimal to boot as
opposed to just having more parameters
or is it mainly like a trick to reduce
inference cost?
>> Yeah. So I think that so the trick with
compute optimal is it is usually like
given a flop budget.
>> Repeat the question.
>> Oh yeah, sorry. Sorry. Yeah. The
question was for parse uh would you ever
choose to loop instead of increasing
parameters? Um and so the trick with
compute optimal is always like given
some flop budget figure out what you
want to hit. Uh it's almost a little bit
contrived in that sense because if you
want a higher quality model, you should
just increase your flops budget and if
you've decided on your model size, just
train longer or um if you're restricted
by your model size, uh then loop longer
or if you have run out of data, then
like pick the the model size that you
think will be uh as overtrained as you
as well trained as you can for for that
size. Um, so I think there are choices
and of course you make all these choices
in the cont in the context of like do I
think it'll get picked up? How am I
going to serve it? Uh, if you're going
to release open source like what what is
the size of model that people can serve
like on your laptop today? Um, so I
think all these choices go into making a
choice. All these things go into making
a choice of how big a model you choose
to train. Um I think like if you just
make the model bigger and train it on
more data, it's always going to get
better. Um but uh yeah, so I think it
really decide it depends on on those
kind of design design points.
>> Maybe another question about uh code
design. So you mentioned at the
beginning different use cases like aente
coding versus let's say um batch
processing of of data. So um what are
the kind of the most dramatic
differences in terms of optimal
architectures that you see across
different use cases right
>> and I guess I mean at the end of the day
of course model developers has to pick
one
>> and tries to not be be reasonable on
>> many use cases.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's a great question. So
I think um one of the big differences so
when you have these agentic looped
workflows, one of the things that
matters a lot is that you want to keep
uh your KV cache as hot as possible. So
if you're doing a big batch processing
thing where you only see each document
once and then you translate it, the KV
cache kind of doesn't uh necessarily
matter as much. Um if you look at
something like the deepseek MLA
attention that is a radical compression
of the KV cache compared to what you
would have um for for another model um
or if you have the model that can uh
process it KV cache in FP8 or FP4 those
are pretty big departures in terms of
the size of the KV cache um that if you
are sensitive to an agentic workflow you
would look at um then of course there
like the biggest one is like causal
attention or non-causal attention right
um so if you're is doing a big batch
processing workflows like for the
longest time Google was just using BERT
models and I think probably still uses
BERT models on search um and that's
because uh you don't really need to be
generating a bunch of tokens on the
other end so you just do that big
birectional attention once you get your
vector out then you stick that in
database do whatever you will with it um
whereas uh you know the the the chat
workflows those processing there's
always going to be this this decode
portion of it. Um I think there have
been intermediate things like I know T5
uh was was at some point a a a choice
that people made um to do some uh
birectional processing and then also
some generation.
>> Okay. Uh maybe one
last question. Oh yeah, my question just
about
it was about everything.
I was just wondering like how does
it cost?
>> Yeah, great question. So the question is
about how does mega kernel work when you
have multiple uh GPUs communication in
the loop. Um we had some very early
preliminary work about this. So turns
out you can also fuse the nickel calls
into the mega kernel if you set it uh up
correctly. Um I think we haven't found a
really great killer use case for that
yet. Um where uh sometimes you're just
bound by the latency of the nickel call
itself. Um so the these are also pieces
of things that you can fuse. I think uh
when Deepseek 4 came out, the Deepseek
foes released a mega kernel for the
mixture of experts inference layer um
that you can run just for that where
they actually did fuse some of those
communication. Um so I think what what
we are starting to see what you're
starting to see more of is as you get to
more of these models, you'll have a
little mega kernel for a part of the for
the part of the computation. Um but you
won't necessarily have a mega kernel for
the whole model. Um, unless of course
you pay the blood, sweat, and tears
price and then re really get really get
the whole thing going.
>> Okay, I think that's all the time we
have. Let's thank Dan again.
Thanks so much for having me.